<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rfc version="3" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-dmarc-failure-reporting-04" submissionType="IETF" category="std" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" obsoletes="7489" consensus="true">

<front>
<title abbrev="DMARC Failure Reporting">Domain-based Message Authentication, Reporting, and Conformance (DMARC) Failure Reporting</title><seriesInfo value="draft-ietf-dmarc-failure-reporting-02" stream="IETF" status="standard" name="Internet-Draft"></seriesInfo>
<author role="editor" surname="Jones" fullname="Steven M Jones"><organization>DMARC.org</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>smj@dmarc.org</email>
</address></author>
<author role="editor" initials="A." surname="Vesely" fullname="Alessandro Vesely"><organization>Tana</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>vesely@tana.it</email>
</address></author>
<date year="2022" month="August" day="11"></date>
<area>Application</area>
<workgroup>DMARC Working Group</workgroup>

<abstract>
<t>Domain-based Message Authentication, Reporting, and Conformance
(DMARC) is a scalable mechanism by which a domain owner can request
feedback about email messages using their domain in the From: address
field. This document describes &quot;failure reports,&quot; or &quot;failed message
reports,&quot; which provide details about individual messages that failed
to authenticate according to the DMARC mechanism.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction"><name>Introduction</name>
<t>Domain-based Message Authentication, Reporting, and Conformance
(DMARC) <xref target="I-D.ietf-dmarc-dmarcbis"></xref> is a scalable mechanism by which a
mail-originating organization can express domain-level policies and
preferences for message validation, disposition, and reporting, that a
mail-receiving organization can use to improve mail handling. This
document focuses on one type of reporting that can be requested under
DMARC.</t>

<t>
Failure reports provide detailed information about the failure of a single
message or a group of similar messages failing for the same reason. They
are meant to aid in cases where a domain owner is unable to detect why
failures reported in aggregate form did occur. It is important to note
these reports can contain either the header or the entire content of a
failed message, which in turn may contain personally identifiable
information, which should be considered when deciding whether to
generate such reports.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="terminology"><name>Terminology and Definitions</name>
<t>This section defines terms used in the rest of the document.</t>
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;NOT RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this
document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref>
when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
<t>Readers are expected to be familiar with the contents of <xref target="I-D.ietf-dmarc-dmarcbis"></xref>,
specifically the terminology and definitions section.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="failure-reports"><name>Failure Reports</name>
<t>Failure reports can supply more detailed information
about messages that failed to authenticate, enabling the Domain Owner
to determine exactly what might be causing those specific failures.</t>
<t>Failure reports are normally generated and sent almost immediately
after the Mail Receiver detects a DMARC failure.  Rather than waiting
for an aggregate report, these reports are useful for quickly
notifying the Domain Owners when there is an authentication failure.
Whether the failure is due to an infrastructure problem or the
message is inauthentic, failure reports also provide more information
about the failed message than is available in an aggregate report.</t>

<t>These reports should include as much of the message header and body as
possible, consistent with the reporting party's privacy policies, to
enable the Domain Owner to diagnose the authentication failure.
</t>

<t>When a Domain Owner requests failure reports for the purpose of
forensic analysis, and the Mail Receiver is willing to provide such
reports, the Mail Receiver generates and sends a message using the
format described in <xref target="RFC6591"></xref>; this document updates that reporting
format, as described in <xref target="reporting-format-update"></xref>.</t>
<t>The destination(s) and nature of the reports are defined by the &quot;ruf&quot;
and &quot;fo&quot; tags as defined in
<xref target="I-D.ietf-dmarc-dmarcbis" sectionFormat="of" section="6.3"/>.</t>

<t>Where multiple URIs are selected to receive failure reports, the
report generator MUST make an attempt to deliver to each of them.</t>

<t>An obvious consideration is the denial-of-service attack that can be
perpetrated by an attacker who sends numerous messages purporting to
be from the intended victim Domain Owner but that fail both SPF and
DKIM; this would cause participating Mail Receivers to send failure
reports to the Domain Owner or its delegate in potentially huge
volumes.  Accordingly, participating Mail Receivers are encouraged to
aggregate these reports as much as is practical, using the Incidents
field of the Abuse Reporting Format (<xref target="RFC5965"></xref>).
Indeed, the aim is not to count each and every failure, but rather to
report different failure paths.
Various aggregation techniques are possible, including the following:</t>

<ul>
<li><t>only send a report to the first recipient of multi-recipient
messages;</t>
</li>
<li><t>store reports for a period of time before sending them, allowing
detection, collection, and reporting of like incidents;</t>
</li>
<li><t>apply rate limiting, such as a maximum number of reports per
minute that will be generated (and the remainder discarded).</t>
</li>
</ul>

<section anchor="reporting-format-update"><name>Reporting Format Update</name>
<t>Operators implementing this specification also implement an augmented
version of <xref target="RFC6591"></xref> as follows:</t>

<ol>
<li><t>A DMARC failure report includes the following ARF header fields,
with the indicated normative requirement levels:</t>

<ul>
<li><t>Identity-Alignment (REQUIRED; defined below)</t>
</li>
<li><t>Delivery-Result (OPTIONAL)</t>
</li>
<li><t>DKIM-Domain, DKIM-Identity, DKIM-Selector (REQUIRED if the
message was signed by DKIM)</t>
</li>
<li><t>DKIM-Canonicalized-Header, DKIM-Canonicalized-Body (OPTIONAL
if the message was signed by DKIM)</t>
</li>
<li><t>SPF-DNS (REQUIRED)</t>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>The &quot;Identity-Alignment&quot; field is defined to contain a comma-
separated list of authentication mechanism names that produced an
aligned identity, or the keyword &quot;none&quot; if none did.  ABNF:</t>
</li>
</ol>

<artwork>  id-align     = &quot;Identity-Alignment:&quot; [CFWS]
                 ( &quot;none&quot; /
                   dmarc-method *( [CFWS] &quot;,&quot; [CFWS] dmarc-method ) )
                 [CFWS]

  dmarc-method = ( &quot;dkim&quot; / &quot;spf&quot; )
                 ; each may appear at most once in an id-align
</artwork>

<ol start="3">
<li>Authentication Failure Type &quot;dmarc&quot; is defined, which is to be
used when a failure report is generated because some or all of
the authentication mechanisms failed to produce aligned
identifiers.  Note that a failure report generator MAY also
independently produce an AFRF message for any or all of the
underlying authentication methods.</li>
</ol>
</section>

<section anchor="verifying-external-destinations"><name>Verifying External Destinations</name>
<t>The procedure described for aggragate reports
<xref target="I-D.ietf-dmarc-aggregate-reporting" sectionFormat="of" section="2.1"/>
applies to failure reports as well.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="transport"><name>Transport</name>
<t>Email streams carrying DMARC failure reports SHOULD provide
DMARC-based authentication, so as to produce "dmarc=pass".
This requirement is
a MUST in case the report is sent through a host having a DMARC record
with a ruf= tag.
Indeed, special care must be taken of authentication in that case, as
failure to authenticate failure reports may result in mail loops.</t>

<t>Reporters SHOULD rate limit the number of failure reports sent
to any recipient to avoid overloading recipient systems.  Again, in case
the reports being sent are in turn at risk of being reported for DMARC
authentication failure, reporters MUST make sure that possible mail loop
are stopped.
</t>

</section>

</section>

<section anchor="privacy-considerations"><name>Privacy Considerations</name>
<t>This section discusses issues specific to private data that
may be included in the DMARC reporting functions.</t>

<section anchor="data-exposure-considerations"><name>Data Exposure Considerations</name>
<t>Failed-message reporting provides message-specific details pertaining
to authentication failures.  Individual reports can contain message
content as well as trace header fields.  Domain Owners are able to
analyze individual reports and attempt to determine root causes of
authentication mechanism failures, gain insight into
misconfigurations or other problems with email and network
infrastructure, or inspect messages for insight into abusive
practices.</t>
<t>These reports may expose sender and recipient identifiers (e.g.,
RFC5322.From addresses), and although the <xref target="RFC6591"></xref> format used for
failed-message reporting supports redaction, failed-message reporting
is capable of exposing the entire message to the report recipient.</t>
<t>Domain Owners requesting reports will receive information about mail
claiming to be from them, which includes mail that was not, in fact,
from them.  Information about the final destination of mail where it
might otherwise be obscured by intermediate systems will therefore be
exposed.</t>
<t>When message-forwarding arrangements exist, Domain Owners requesting
reports will also receive information about mail forwarded to domains
that were not originally part of their messages' recipient lists.
This means that destination domains previously unknown to the Domain
Owner may now become visible.</t>
<t>Disclosure of information about the messages is being requested by
the entity generating the email in the first place, i.e., the Domain
Owner and not the Mail Receiver, so this may not fit squarely within
existing privacy policy provisions.  For some providers,
failed-message reporting is viewed as a function
similar to complaint reporting about spamming or phishing and is
treated similarly under the privacy policy.  Report generators (i.e.,
Mail Receivers) are encouraged to review their reporting limitations
under such policies before enabling DMARC reporting.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="report-recipients"><name>Report Recipients</name>
<t>A DMARC record can specify that reports should be sent to an
intermediary operating on behalf of the Domain Owner.  This is done
when the Domain Owner contracts with an entity to monitor mail
streams for abuse and performance issues.  Receipt by third parties
of such data may or may not be permitted by the Mail Receiver's
privacy policy, terms of use, or other similar governing document.
Domain Owners and Mail Receivers should both review and understand if
their own internal policies constrain the use and transmission of
DMARC reporting.</t>
<t>Some potential exists for report recipients to perform traffic
analysis, making it possible to obtain metadata about the Receiver's
traffic.  In addition to verifying compliance with policies,
Receivers need to consider that before sending reports to a third
party.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations"><name>Security Considerations</name>
<t>Considerations discussed in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dmarc-dmarcbis" sectionFormat="of" section="11"/> apply.</t>

<t>In addition, note that Organizational Domains are only an approximation
to actual domain ownership.  Therefore, reports may be sent to someone
unrelated to the actual sender or domain owner.  That makes considerations
in <xref target="data-exposure-considerations"/> all the more relevant.</t>

</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references><name>Normative References</name>
<!-- xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"/ -->
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<!-- xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml"/ -->
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6591.xml"/>
<!-- xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7489.xml"/ -->
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dmarc-dmarcbis.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dmarc-aggregate-reporting.xml"/>
</references>
<references><name>Informative References</name>
<!-- xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2142.xml"/ -->
<!-- xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml"/ -->
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5965.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
</references>

<section anchor="examples"><name>Examples</name>
<t>This section presents some examples related to the use of DMARC
reporting functions.</t>

<section anchor="entire-domain-monitoring-only-per-message-reports"><name>Entire Domain, Monitoring Only, Per-Message Reports</name>
<t>The owners of the domain "example.com" have deployed SPF and DKIM on
their messaging infrastructure.  As described in,
<xref target="I-D.ietf-dmarc-aggregate-reporting" sectionFormat="of" section="B.2.1"/>
they have used the aggregate
reporting to discover some messaging systems that had not yet
implemented DKIM correctly.  However, they are still seeing periodic
authentication failures.  In order to diagnose these intermittent
problems, they wish to request per-message failure reports when
authentication failures occur.</t>
<t>Not all Receivers will honor such a request, but the Domain Owner
feels that any reports it does receive will be helpful enough to
justify publishing this record.  The default per-message report
format (<xref target="RFC6591"></xref>) meets the Domain Owner's needs in this scenario.</t>
<t>The Domain Owner accomplishes this by adding the following to its
policy record:</t>

<ul>
<li>Per-message failure reports should be sent via email to the
address &quot;auth-reports@example.com&quot;
(&quot;ruf=mailto:auth-reports@example.com&quot;)</li>
</ul>
<t>The updated DMARC policy record might look like this when retrieved using a
common command-line tool (the output shown would appear on a single
line but is wrapped here for publication):</t>

<artwork>  % dig +short TXT _dmarc.example.com.
  &quot;v=DMARC1; p=none; rua=mailto:dmarc-feedback@example.com;
   ruf=mailto:auth-reports@example.com&quot;
</artwork>
<t>To publish such a record, the DNS administrator for the Domain Owner
might create an entry like the following in the appropriate zone file
(following the conventional zone file format):</t>

<artwork>  ; DMARC record for the domain example.com

  _dmarc  IN TXT ( &quot;v=DMARC1; p=none; &quot;
                    &quot;rua=mailto:dmarc-feedback@example.com; &quot;
                    &quot;ruf=mailto:auth-reports@example.com&quot; )
</artwork>
</section>

<section anchor="per-message-failure-reports-directed-to-third-party">
<name>Per-Message Failure Reports Directed to Third Party</name>
<t>The Domain Owner from the previous example is maintaining the same
policy but now wishes to have a third party receive and process the
per-message failure reports.  Again, not all Receivers will honor
this request, but those that do may implement additional checks to
validate that the third party wishes to receive the failure reports
for this domain.</t>
<t>The Domain Owner needs to alter its policy record from <xref target="entire-domain-monitoring-only-per-message-reports"></xref>
as follows:</t>

<ul>
<li>Per-message failure reports should be sent via email to the
address &quot;auth-reports@thirdparty.example.net&quot;
(&quot;ruf=mailto:auth-reports@thirdparty.example.net&quot;)</li>
</ul>
<t>The DMARC policy record might look like this when retrieved using a
common command-line tool (the output shown would appear on a single
line but is wrapped here for publication):</t>

<artwork>  % dig +short TXT _dmarc.example.com.
  &quot;v=DMARC1; p=none; rua=mailto:dmarc-feedback@example.com;
   ruf=mailto:auth-reports@thirdparty.example.net&quot;
</artwork>
<t>To publish such a record, the DNS administrator for the Domain Owner
might create an entry like the following in the appropriate zone file
(following the conventional zone file format):</t>

<artwork>  ; DMARC record for the domain example.com

  _dmarc IN TXT ( &quot;v=DMARC1; p=none; &quot;
                  &quot;rua=mailto:dmarc-feedback@example.com; &quot;
                  &quot;ruf=mailto:auth-reports@thirdparty.example.net&quot; )
</artwork>
<t>Because the address used in the &quot;ruf&quot; tag is outside the
Organizational Domain in which this record is published, conforming
Receivers will implement additional checks as described in
<xref target="verifying-external-destinations"></xref> of this document.  In order to pass these additional
checks, the third party will need to publish an additional DNS record
as follows:</t>

<ul>
<li>Given the DMARC record published by the Domain Owner at
&quot;_dmarc.example.com&quot;, the DNS administrator for the third party
will need to publish a TXT resource record at
&quot;example.com._report._dmarc.thirdparty.example.net&quot; with the value
&quot;v=DMARC1;&quot;.</li>
</ul>
<t>The resulting DNS record might look like this when retrieved using a
common command-line tool (the output shown would appear on a single
line but is wrapped here for publication):</t>

<artwork>  % dig +short TXT example.com._report._dmarc.thirdparty.example.net
  &quot;v=DMARC1;&quot;
</artwork>
<t>To publish such a record, the DNS administrator for example.net might
create an entry like the following in the appropriate zone file
(following the conventional zone file format):</t>

<artwork>  ; zone file for thirdparty.example.net
  ; Accept DMARC failure reports on behalf of example.com

  example.com._report._dmarc   IN   TXT    &quot;v=DMARC1;&quot;
</artwork>
<t>Intermediaries and other third parties should refer to
<xref target="verifying-external-destinations"></xref> for the full details of this
mechanism.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="report-format-example">
<name>Report Format Example</name>
<t>This is the full content of a failure message, including the header.</t>
<figure>
<sourcecode>
Received: from generator.example (generator.example [192.0.2.1])
  (TLS: TLS1.3,256bits,ECDHE_RSA_AES_256_GCM_SHA384)
  by mail.consumer.example with ESMTPS
  id 00000000005DC0DD.0000442E; Tue, 19 Jul 2022 07:57:50 +0200
DKIM-Signature: v=1; a=rsa-sha256; c=relaxed/simple;
  d=generator.example; s=mail; t=1658210268;
  bh=rCrh1aFDE8d/Fltt8wbcu48bLOu4OM23QXqphUZPAIM=;
  h=From:To:Date:Subject:From;
  b=IND9JkuwF9/5841kzxMbPeej0VYimVzNKozR2R89M8eYO2zOlCBblx507Gz0YK7mE
   /h6pslWm0ODBVFzLlwY9CXv4Vu62QsN0RBIXHPjEXOkoM2VCD5zCd+5i5dtCFX7Mxh
   LThb2ZJ3efklbSB9RQRwxcmRvCPV7z6lt/Ds9sucVE1RDODYHjx+iWnAUQrlos6ZQb
   u/YOUGjf60LPpyljfPu3EpFwo80mSHyQlP/4S5KEykgPQMgCqLPPKvJwu1aAIDj+jG
   q2ylO3fmc/ERDeDWACtR67YNabEKBWtjqCRLNxKttazViJTZ5drcLfpX0853KoougX
   Rltp7zdoLdy4A==
From: DMARC Filter &lt;DMARC@generator.example&gt;
To: dmarcfail@consumer.example
Date: Tue, 19 Jul 2022 00:57:48 -0500 (CDT)
Subject: FW: This is the original subject
Mime-Version: 1.0
Content-Type: multipart/report; report-type=feedback-report;
  boundary="=_mime_boundary_"
Message-Id: &lt;20220719055748.4AE9D403CC@generator.example&gt;

This is a MIME-formatted message.  If you see this text it means that
your E-mail software does not support MIME-formatted messages.

--=_mime_boundary_
Content-Type: text/plain; charset=utf-8
Content-Disposition: inline
Content-Transfer-Encoding: 7bit

This is an authentication failure report for an email message
received from IP 192.0.2.2 on Tue, 19 Jul 2022 00:57:48 -0500.

--=_mime_boundary_
Content-Type: message/feedback-report
Content-Transfer-Encoding: 7bit

Feedback-Type: auth-failure
Version: 1
User-Agent: DMARC-Filter/1.2.3
Auth-Failure: signature
Authentication-Results: generator.example;
  dmarc=fail header.from=consumer.example
Original-Envelope-Id: 65E1A3F0A0
Original-Mail-From: author=generator.example@forwarder.example
Source-IP: 192.0.2.2
Source-Port: 12345
Reported-Domain: consumer.example

--=_mime_boundary_
Content-Type: text/rfc822-headers; charset=utf-8
Content-Transfer-Encoding: 7bit

Authentication-Results: generator.example;
  dkim=permerror header.d=forwarder.example header.b="EjCbN/c3";
  dkim=temperror header.d=forwarder.example header.b="mQ8GEWPc";
  dkim=permerror header.d=consumer.example header.b="hETrymCb";
  dkim=neutral header.d=consumer.example header.b="C2nsAp3A";
Received: from mail.forwarder.example (localhost [127.0.0.1])
  by mail.forwarder.example (Postfix) with ESMTP id 4Ln7Qw4fnvz6Bq
  for &lt;x@generator.example&gt;; Tue, 19 Jul 2022 07:57:44 +0200
DKIM-Signature: v=1; a=ed25519-sha256; c=relaxed/relaxed;
  d=forwarder.example; s=dnswl-ed25519-59hs; t=1658210264;
  x=1663210264; bh=KYH/g7ForvDbnyyDLYSjauMYMW6sEIqu75/9w3OIONg=;
  h=Message-ID:Date:List-Id:List-Archive:List-Post:List-Help:
   List-Subscribe:List-Unsubscribe:List-Owner:MIME-Version:Subject:To:
   References:From:In-Reply-To:Content-Type:Content-Transfer-Encoding:
   autocrypt:cc:content-transfer-encoding:content-type:date:from:
   in-reply-to:message-id:mime-version:openpgp:references:subject:to;
  b=EjCbN/c3bTU4QkZH/zwTbYxBDp0k8kpmWSXh5h1M7T8J4vtRo+hvafJazT3ZRgq+7
   +4dzEQwUhl+NOJYXXNUAA==
DKIM-Signature: v=1; a=rsa-sha256; c=relaxed/relaxed;
  d=forwarder.example; s=dnswl-rsa-wgJg; t=1658210264; x=1663210264;
  bh=KYH/g7ForvDbnyyDLYSjauMYMW6sEIqu75/9w3OIONg=;
  h=Message-ID:Date:List-Id:List-Archive:List-Post:List-Help:
   List-Subscribe:List-Unsubscribe:List-Owner:MIME-Version:Subject:To:
   References:From:In-Reply-To:Content-Type:Content-Transfer-Encoding:
   autocrypt:cc:content-transfer-encoding:content-type:date:from:
   in-reply-to:message-id:mime-version:openpgp:references:subject:to;
  b=mQ8GEWPcVpBpeqQ88pcbXpGHBT0J/Rwi8Zd2WZTXWWneQGRCOJLRcbBJpjqnrwtqd
   76IqawH86tihz4Z/12J1GBCdNx1gfazsoI3yaqfooRDYg0mSyZHrYhQBmodnPcqZj4
   /25L5278sc/UNrYO9az2n7R/skbVZ0bvSo2eEiGU8fcpO8+a5SKNYskhaviAI4eGIB
   iRMdEP7gP8dESdnZguNbY5HI32UMDpPPNqajzd/BgcqbveYpRrWCDOhcY47POV7GHM
   i/KLHiZXtJsL3/Pr/4TL+HTjdX8EDSsy1K5/JCvJCFsJHnSvkEaJQGLn/2m03eW9r8
   9w1bQ90aY+VCQ==
X-Original-To: users@forwarder.example
Received: from mail.consumer.example (mail.consumer.example [192.0.2.4])
  (using TLSv1.3 with cipher TLS_AES_256_GCM_SHA384 (256/256 bits)
   key-exchange ECDHE (P-256) server-signature ECDSA (P-384)
   server-digest SHA384)
  (Client did not present a certificate)
  by mail.forwarder.example (Postfix) with ESMTPS id 4Ln7Qs55xmz4nP
  for &lt;users@forwarder.example&gt;; Tue, 19 Jul 2022 07:57:41 +0200 (CEST)
Authentication-Results: mail.forwarder.example;
  arc=none smtp.remote-ip=192.0.2.4
Authentication-Results: mail.forwarder.example;
  dkim=pass (512-bit key; secure) header.d=consumer.example
   header.i=@consumer.example header.a=ed25519-sha256
   header.s=epsilon header.b=hETrymCb;
  dkim=pass (1152-bit key; secure) header.d=consumer.example
   header.i=@consumer.example header.a=rsa-sha256
   header.s=delta header.b=C2nsAp3A
DKIM-Signature: v=1; a=ed25519-sha256; c=relaxed/relaxed;
  d=consumer.example; s=epsilon; t=1658210255;
  bh=KYH/g7ForvDbnyyDLYSjauMYMW6sEIqu75/9w3OIONg=;
  h=Date:Subject:To:References:From:In-Reply-To;
  b=hETrymCbz6T1Dyo5dCG9dk8rPykKLdhJCPFeJ9TiiP/kaoN2afpUYtj+SrI+I83lp
   p1F/FfYSGy7zz3Q3OdxBA==
DKIM-Signature: v=1; a=rsa-sha256; c=relaxed/relaxed;
  d=consumer.example; s=delta; t=1658210255;
  bh=KYH/g7ForvDbnyyDLYSjauMYMW6sEIqu75/9w3OIONg=;
  h=Date:To:References:From:In-Reply-To;
  b=C2nsAp3AMNX33Nq7nN/StPo921xE3XGF8Ju3iAKdYB3EKhsril0N5IjWGlglJECst
   jLNKSo7KWZZ2lkH/dVZ9Rs1GHT2uaKy1sc/xmNIC5rHdhrxammiwpTSo4PsT8disfc
   3DVF6Q62n0EsdLFqcw1KY8A9inFqYKY2tqoo+y4zMtItqCYx3xjsj3I0IFLuX
Author: Message Author &lt;author@consumer.example&gt;
Received: from [192.0.2.8] (host-8-2-0-192.isp.example [192.0.2.8])
  (AUTH: CRAM-MD5 uXDGrn@SYT0/k, TLS: TLS1.3,128bits,
  ECDHE_RSA_AES_128_GCM_SHA256)
  by mail.consumer.example with ESMTPSA
  id 00000000005DC076.00004417; Tue, 19 Jul 2022 07:57:35 +0200
Message-ID: &lt;2431dc66-b010-c9cc-4f2b-a1f889f8bdb4@consumer.example&gt;
Date: Tue, 19 Jul 2022 07:57:33 +0200
List-Id: &lt;users.forwarder.example&gt;
List-Post: &lt;mailto:users@forwarder.example&gt;
List-Help: &lt;mailto:users+help@forwarder.example&gt;
List-Subscribe: &lt;mailto:users+subscribe@forwarder.example&gt;
List-Unsubscribe: &lt;mailto:users+unsubscribe@forwarder.example&gt;
List-Owner: &lt;mailto:users+owner@forwarder.example&gt;
Precedence: list
MIME-Version: 1.0
Subject: This is the original subject
Content-Language: en-US
To: users@forwarder.example
Authentication-Results: consumer.example; auth=pass (details omitted)
From: Message Author &lt;author@consumer.example&gt;
In-Reply-To: &lt;20220718102753.0f6d9dde.cel@example.com&gt;
Content-Type: text/plain; charset=UTF-8; format=flowed
Content-Transfer-Encoding: 8bit

--=_mime_boundary_--
</sourcecode>
</figure>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="change-log">
<name>Change Log</name>
<t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this section prior to publication.]</t>

<dl newline="false" indent="4">
	<dt>00 to 01</dt>
	<dd>
		<ul>
			<li>Replace references to RFC7489 with references to I-D.ietf-dmarc-dmarcbis.</li>
			<li>Replace the 2nd paragraph in the Introduction with the text proposed by Ned
				for Ticket #55, which enjoys some consensus:<br/>
				https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/msg/dmarc/HptVyJ9SgrfxWRbeGwORagPrhCw</li>
			<li>Strike a spurious sentence about criticality of feedback, which was
				meant for feedback in general, not failure reports.  In fact, failure
				reports are not critical to establishing and maintaining accurate authentication
				deployments.  Still attributable to Ticket #55.</li>
			<li>Remove the content of section "Verifying External Destinations"
				and refer to I-D.ietf-dmarc-aggregate-reporting.</li>
			<li>Remove the content of section "Security Considerations"
				and refer to I-D.ietf-dmarc-dmarcbis.</li>
			<li>Slightly tweak the wording of the example in Appendix A.1
				so that it makes sense standing alone.</li>
			<li>Remove the sentence containing "must include any URI(s)",
				as the issue arose <eref target="https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/msg/dmarc/mFk0qiTCy8tzghRvcxus01W_Blw"/>.</li>
			<li>Add paragraph in Security Considerations, noting that
				note that Organizational Domains are only an approximation...</li>
			<li>Add a Transport section, mentioning DMARC conformance and
				failure report mail loops (Ticket #28).</li>
		</ul>
	</dd>
	<dt>01 to 02</dt>
	<dd>
		<ul>
			<li>Add a sentence to make clear that counting failures is not the aim.</li>
		</ul>
	</dd>
	<dt>02 to 03</dt>
	<dd>
		<ul>
			<li>Updated references.</li>
		</ul>
	</dd>
	<dt>03 to 04</dt>
	<dd>
		<ul>
			<li>Add an example report.</li>
			<li>Remove the old Acknowledgements section.</li>
		</ul>
	</dd>

</dl>
</section>

</back>

</rfc>
